Governor's Efficiency Study Commission SR.397
State Archives of North Carolina
Governor's Efficiency Study Commission Record Group
1973 - 1978
SR.397
397
397.1
MARS ID 397
Committee reports Manuscripts
Contains mainly typed and hand written manuscript materials. Also contains some print materials and a few photographs.
52.00 65.00
Governor's Efficiency Study Commission.
North Carolina, Office of the Governor.
State Archives of North Carolina
Box Governor's Efficiency Study Commission Record Group
Transfered out (from us)
Organization
Arranged into three main series: Commission Files, Summaries and Working Files. The Commission Files Series is arranged alphabetically by folder title. The Summaries Series is arranged numerically and then alphabetically according to a number scheme originally assigned by the agency
Access to Collection
Collection is open for research.
Historical Note
On January 16th, 1973, Governor James E. Holshouser, Jr. issued Executive Order Number 1 authorizing the creation of the Governor's Efficiency Study Commission to conduct intensive research on programs and procedures involving the administrative and operating functions of all departments, agencies and commissions of the state government. The Executive Order empowered the representatives of the Commission to investigate and analyze the different facets of state government as they deemed fit. It also directed every office and employee within the Governor's authority to provide all information and assistance necessary for the Commission to make its determinations. According to Governor Holshouser, this effort would complement the reorganization plan of the early 1970s that revised, in stages, the basic structure of state government and its programs.
The Governor appointed Archie K. Davis as the Chairman. Davis had served as Chair to the Board of Wachovia Bank and Trust, President and Chairman of the Research Triangle Foundation, President of the American Bankers Association, and President of the United States Chamber of Commerce. As Chairman, Davis was charged with authority to form a non-profit corporation and to secure the personnel, facilities, and financial assistance to carry out the study. The order further provided that the officers and directors of the corporation would be elected following consultation with the governor. These members were composed of industry, business, educational, and professional representatives. The order also named Warren King and Associates, a private consulting firm, to coordinate the project and advise the Commission.
The study examined the activities of almost all of the executive branch of state government, including the offices of the governor, lieutenant governor, the nine executive departments whose secretaries answer to the governor and the university system. Additionally, the six departments headed by elected members of the Council of State participated. Members of the Executive Committee directly oversaw study teams to evaluate seven specific government functions: General Government, Regulatory and Protective, Social and Human Resources, Transportation, Agricultural and Natural Resources, Public Instruction, and Higher Education. Team members conducted studies through interviews, reports from internal and external sources, compilation and accumulation of research data, and personal observations. They then formulated recommendations which were submitted to the Executive Committee and the Governor in a series of Final Reports. These recommendations, which encompassed everything from the major restructuring of state agencies to the money and time spent typing specific forms, were either implemented, found unacceptable, or marked for further study. The Commission disbanded at the end of 1973. Initially, the work was continued by the by Office of Administrative Management Analysis. Later this office was replaced by the Office of Administrative Analysis, which was created to reduce costs and increase efficiency of the state government.
Before the end of 1973, the Governor's Efficiency Study Commission had submitted almost seven hundred recommendations. Some recommendations required legislative action, but most could be implemented administratively. The Holshouser Administration instituted almost six hundred of the recommendations over a period of twenty-four months and was credited with an annual savings of over sixty-three million dollars. Some observations have been referenced in later years as future governors and state officials addressed issues of efficiency and government change. Occasionally, recommendations originally marked for more study or considered unacceptable in 1973 were implemented during future terms.
Governor, Office of the
Custodial History
The bulk of the records were transferred from the custody of the Department of Administration to the State Archives on 12/17/1975.
Governor's Office (MARS # 67)
Related Collections
Additional information on topics found in this collection may be found in the Manuscript and Archives Reference System (MARS) http://mars.archives.ncdcr.gov/BasicSearch.aspx
Related materials may also exist in the records of the Department of Administration, Office and Administrative Analylis, MARS No. 40.70 and the Department of Administration, Office of Policy and Planning, MARS No. 40.52 and also in the Records of Governor James Holshouser, MARS No. 371.
A small amount of materials related to the Governor's Efficiency Study Commission can be found in the Collection of Archie K. Davis Papers located at the University of North Carolina, Wilson Library in Chapel Hill, North Carolina.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, minutes, memoranda, notes, forms, reports, statistical data in a variety of formats, press materials, printed matter, some published materials and a few photographs along with other manuscript materials specific to a variety of government functions. Ranging from 1951 to 1978, the collection is broken into three series. The Commission Files Series contains the materials pertaining to the creation and administration of the Commission. The Summaries Series includes summaries and Final Reports from study teams. The Working Files Series contains the materials accumulated and created by the study teams throughout the course of the study. The bulk of the materials are from 1973 to 1975. Those materials dated prior to 1973 are most often materials accumulated by the teams for their research. Materials dated after 1973 are from the Office of Administrative Management Analysis (before 1975) and the Office of Administrative Analylis (after 1975). There is a small amount of materials dated between 1975 and 1978, which generally refers to the overall results of the Commission and the progress of some of the implemented recommendations.
Scope and Content
State expenditures more than doubled in the decade between 1963 and 1973--a reflection of significant increases in government costs and of expanded services in response to the demands of a complex society. Governor James E. Holshouser, Jr., addressed the problem of spiraling costs in January of 1973 when he issued an executive order creating the Governor's Efficiency Study Commission, an independent, non-partisan body composed solely of members of the private sector. The commission was charged with finding ways to improve the efficiency and economy of state government administration in its everyday operations. According to Governor Holshouser, this effort would complement the reorganization plan of the early 1970s that revised in stages the basic structure of state government and its programs.
Under terms of the order creating the Governor's Efficiency Study Commission, the governor designated a chairman with authority to form a non-profit corporation and to secure the personnel, facilities, and financial assistance to carry out the study. The order further provided that the officers and directors of the corporation would be elected as provided by law following consultation with the governor. The order also named a private consulting firm to coordinate the project and advise the commission. The study encompassed the activities of almost all of the executive branch of state government--the offices of the governor, lieutenant governor, the nine executive departments whose secretaries answer to the governor--and the university system. The heads of these offices, agencies, and institutions were required to submit all information requested by the commission's members and its consultants. Additionally, the six departments headed by elected members of the Council of State were asked to participate in the study and accepted the invitation. After completion of its work, the commission was required to submit to the governor a report of its findings and recommendations.
Before the end of 1973 the Governor's Efficiency Study Commission had submitted almost seven hundred recommendations. Some of these would require legislative action, but most could be implemented administratively. The Holshouser administration instituted almost six hundred of the recommendations over a period of twenty-four months at annual savings of over sixty-three million dollars. Subsequent to the termination of the study commission at the end of the year, an Office of Administrative Analysis was established within the Department of Administration to build on the commission's mission of reducing costs and increasing the efficiency of state government.
REFERENCES: S.L., 1973, Executive Order No. 1, 16 January 1973. Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. SURVEY AND RECOMMENDATIONS.
Raleigh, 1973. Mitchell, Memory F., ed. ADDRESSES AND PUBLIC PAPERS OF JAMES EUBERT
HOLSHOUSER, JR., GOVERNOR OF NORTH CAROLINA, 1973-1977. Raleigh:
Division of Archives and History, 1978. Pp. xxvi-xxvii, 62-65, 242,
134-135, 389-397, 475.
Scope and Content
Minutes and working files of the commission. Also includes material from the Dept. of Administration, Office of Administrative Analysis.
TRANSFERRED DATES VOLUME TO ARCHIVES
Transf. 12/17/75 1973-1974 17 boxes 12-17-75
Transf. 12/17/75 1973-1974 4 boxes 12-17-75 (labeled Dept. of Administration, Office of Administrative Analysis)
Davis, Archie K.; Holshouser, James E., Governor
North Carolina. Office of the Governor; North Carolina. Governor's Efficiency Study Commission; North Carolina. Department of Administration.; North Carolina. Department of Administration; North Carolina. Office of Administrative Analysis; North Carolina. Governor's Efficiency Study Commission (1973); North Carolina. Office of the Governor
Administrative Agencies; Management; Administrative Agencies; Management
- Commission Files, SR.397.1; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission.
  - Administration, 1973; 3383; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Administration)
  - Administrative Analysis Program Plan with Requisitions, 1973-1977; 3384; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Administrative Analysis Program Plan with Requisitions)
  - Analysis of Implementation Progress, 1973-1974; 3385; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Analysis of Implementation Progress)
  - Career Newsletter, 1971-1972; 3386; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Career Newsletter)
  - Carpooling Project, 1977; 3387; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Carpooling Project)
  - Continuing Education Unit Report by National University Extension Association, undated; 3388; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Continuing Education Unit Report by National University Extension Association)
  - Correspondence, 1975; 3389; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Correspondence)
  - Davis, Archie K. of Wachovia Bank and Trust, Chairman Correspondence, 1974-1975; 3390; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Davis, Archie K. of Wachovia Bank and Trust, Chairman Correspondence)
  - Executive Order, 1973; 3391; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Executive Order)
  - Forward and Overview, 1973; 3392; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Forward and Overview)
  - Furniture and Equipment, 1976; 3393; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Furniture and Equipment)
  - Graphs, 1973-1974; 3394; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Graphs)
  - Governor's Committee on State Government Reorganization Report, 1971-1972; 3395; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Governor's Committee on State Government Reorganization Report)
  - Governor's Reports, 1974; 3396; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Governor's Reports)
  - Hand-outs, undated; 3397; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Hand-outs)
  - Implementation Progress Report, 1975; 3398; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Implementation Progress Report)
  - Implementation Status Analysis, 1974-1975; 3399; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Implementation Status Analysis)
  - Individual Recommendation Action Report, 1974-1976; 3400; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Individual Recommendation Action Report)
  - Land Records Management Program, 1977; 3401; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Land Records Management Program)
  - Mail Study, 1968-1976; 3402; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Mail Study)
  - Legislative Bills Affecting Efficiency Study, 1974; 3403; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Bills Affecting Efficiency Study)
  - Legislative Miscellaneous, undated; 3404; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Miscellaneous)
  - Legislative Program, 1974; 3405; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Program)
  - Legislative Recommendations, undated; 3406; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Recommendations)
  - Legislative Recommendations: More Study, 1974-1975; 3407; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Recommendations: More Study)
  - Legislative Recommendations: To be Introduced Next Session, 1973-1975; 3408; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Recommendations: To be Introduced Next Session)
  - Legislative Recommendations: Unacceptable, 1974; 3409; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Legislative Recommendations: Unacceptable)
  - Management Task Force Final Report, 1977; 3410; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Management Task Force Final Report)
  - Medicaid, 1976-1977; 3411; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Medicaid)
  - Meeting Minutes: Executive Committee, 1973; 3412; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Meeting Minutes: Executive Committee)
  - Meeting Minutes: Internal Implementation Coordinators, 1974; 3413; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Meeting Minutes: Internal Implementation Coordinators)
  - Members Listing, 1974; 3414; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Members Listing)
  - Memorandums, 1975; 3415; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Memorandums)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973; 3416; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous)
  - Miscellaneous A, 1974; 3417; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous A)
  - Miscellaneous C, 1974; 3418; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous C)
  - Miscellaneous F, 1974; 3419; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous F)
  - Miscellaneous K, 1974; 3420; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous K)
  - Miscellaneous M, 1974; 3421; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous M)
  - Miscellaneous W, 1974; 3422; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous W)
  - Miscellaneous X, Y and Z, 1974; 3423; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Miscellaneous X, Y and Z)
  - National Science Foundation, 1974; 3424; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder National Science Foundation)
  - News Release: Chairman Archie K. Davis, 1973; 3425; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder News Release: Chairman Archie K. Davis)
  - News Release: Governor Holshouser, 1974; 3426; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder News Release: Governor Holshouser)
  - News Release: Progress Report on Implementation of Efficiency Study, 1974; 3427; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder News Release: Progress Report on Implementation of Efficiency Study)
  - North Carolina State Local Task Force, "New Directions", 1973; 3428; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder North Carolina State Local Task Force, "New Directions")
  - Office of Administrative Analysis, 1975-1978; 3429; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Office of Administrative Analysis)
  - Office of Administrative Analysis: Organization File, 1976; 3430; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Office of Administrative Analysis: Organization File)
  - Office of Administrative Analysis: Space Administration Section, 1976; 3431; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Office of Administrative Analysis: Space Administration Section)
  - Office of Administrative Analysis: Space Issues, 1973; 3432; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Office of Administrative Analysis: Space Issues)
  - Official Roster Credits Page, 1973; 3433; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Official Roster Credits Page)
  - Operating Guide and Case Study, 1970; 3434; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Operating Guide and Case Study)
  - Periodic Reports, 1975-1976; 3435; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Periodic Reports)
  - Press Releases, 1974; 3436; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Press Releases)
  - Space Management Section, 1976; 3437; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Space Management Section)
  - Statistical Information, 1975-1977; 3438; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Statistical Information)
  - Survey Sample Format, 1977; 3439; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Survey Sample Format)
  - Warren King and Associates, 1974; 3440; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Warren King and Associates)
  - Weiner, Arthur E. Correspondence, 1974; 3441; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Weiner, Arthur E. Correspondence)
  - Work Force Reduction, 1977; 3442; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Work Force Reduction)
  - Work Force Reduction Final Report, 1977; 3443; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Work Force Reduction Final Report)
- Summaries, SR.397.2; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission.
  - Table of Contents, 1973; 3444; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Table of Contents)
  - Mailing List for Final Reports, 1973; 3445; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder Mailing List for Final Reports)
  - 1 Governor's Office, 1973; 3446; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 1 Governor's Office)
  - 2 Lieutenant Governor's Office, 1973; 3447; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 2 Lieutenant Governor's Office)
  - 3 Department of Administration, 1973; 3448; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3 Department of Administration)
  - 3A Office of the Budget, 1973; 3449; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3A Office of the Budget)
  - 3B Office of Property and Construction, 1973; 3450; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3B Office of Property and Construction)
  - 3C Office of Purchase and Contract, 1973; 3451; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3C Office of Purchase and Contract)
  - 3D Office of State Planning, 1973; 3452; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3D Office of State Planning)
  - 3E Office of Management Systems, 1973; 3453; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3E Office of Management Systems)
  - 3F Office of State Personnel, 1973; 3454; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3F Office of State Personnel)
  - 3G Office of General Services, 1973; 3455; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3G Office of General Services)
  - 3H Office of State and Federal Relations, 1973; 3456; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 3H Office of State and Federal Relations)
  - 4 Department of the Secretary of State, 1973; 3457; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 4 Department of the Secretary of State)
  - 6 Department of State Treasurer, 1973; 3458; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 6 Department of State Treasurer)
  - 7 Department of Justice, 1973; 3459; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 7 Department of Justice)
  - 8 Department of Revenue, 1973; 3460; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8 Department of Revenue)
  - 8A Accounting Division, 1973; 3461; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8A Accounting Division)
  - 8B Individual Income Tax, 1973; 3462; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8B Individual Income Tax)
  - 8C Inheritance and Gift Tax, 1973; 3463; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8C Inheritance and Gift Tax)
  - 8D Privilege, Beverage and Cigarette Tax, 1973; 3464; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8D Privilege, Beverage and Cigarette Tax)
  - 8E Intangibles, 1973; 3465; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8E Intangibles)
  - 8F Corporate Income Tax, 1973; 3466; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8F Corporate Income Tax)
  - 8G Sales and Use Tax, 1973; 3467; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8G Sales and Use Tax)
  - 8H Gas Tax, 1973; 3468; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8H Gas Tax)
  - 8I Ad Valorum Tax, 1973; 3469; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8I Ad Valorum Tax)
  - 8J Planning and Processing, 1973; 3470; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8J Planning and Processing)
  - 8K Audit and Collection, 1973; 3471; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8K Audit and Collection)
  - 8M Tax Research, 1973; 3472; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 8M Tax Research)
  - 9 Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs, 1973; 3473; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 9 Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs)
  - 9A State Civil Defense Agency, 1973; 3474; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 9A State Civil Defense Agency)
  - 9B Adjutant General's Office, 1973; 3475; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 9B Adjutant General's Office)
  - 9C Veterans' Affairs, 1973; 3476; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 9C Veterans' Affairs)
  - 10 Department of Commerce, 1973; 3477; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 10 Department of Commerce)
  - 10A Regulatory Groups: State Funded, 1973; 3478; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 10A Regulatory Groups: State Funded)
  - 10B Regulatory Groups: Non State Funded, 1973; 3479; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 10B Regulatory Groups: Non State Funded)
  - 10C Board of Alcoholic Control, 1973; 3480; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 10C Board of Alcoholic Control)
  - 10D Employment Security Commission, 1973; 3481; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 10D Employment Security Commission)
  - 11 Department of Labor, 1973; 3482; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 11 Department of Labor)
  - 12 Department of Social Rehabilitation and Control, 1973; 3483; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 12 Department of Social Rehabilitation and Control)
  - 12A Office of Correction, 1973; 3484; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission.
  - 12B Office of Youth Development, 1973; 3485; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 12B Office of Youth Development)
  - 12C Enterprises Revolving Fund, 1973; 3486; Governor's Efficiency Study Commission. (Folder 12C Enterprises Revolving Fund)